Inventory of the Papers of Monroe Leigh, 1941 - 2001
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
Inventory of the Papers of Monroe Leigh 1941 - 2001
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 04-2
This collection contains 56 boxes of files (22.4 linear feet).
The Papers of Monroe Leigh include materials from his days as a University of Virginia Law Student and Adjunct Professor, the years he practiced law with Steptoe & Johnson and the work he did as Legal Advisor the State Department. A large portion of the documents pertain to his work on war crimes and the formation of the International Criminal Court (ICC).
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born in 1919, Monroe Leigh grew up in Halifax, Virginia before graduating from Hampton-Sydney College in 1940 and then completing his law degree at the University of Virginia Law School in 1947. When the United States entered World War II while Leigh was a law student, he paused his legal studies to enlist in the Army where he served as a Captain in the Ninth Air Force in Europe. During his tenure at the University of Virginia Law School, Leigh served as the Editor-In-Chief of the Virginia Law Review.
After completing his law degree, Leigh moved to Washington, D.C. to work at Covington, Burling, Rublee, Acheson & Shorb. Continuing his active interest in international law, he joined the first U. S. Mission to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) in 1951. Two years later Leigh served on the legal staff of the Department of Defense, specializing in international affairs. By 1959, Leigh decided to return to private practice with the law firm of Steptoe & Johnson, ultimately assuming the role of the managing partner in their international law department. While he focused on international disputes and developed his expertise on public international law and international trade law, Leigh also began his long tenure at the University of Virginia Law School as an adjunct professor on international trade law.
In 1975, Leigh was called upon by then Secretary of State Henry Kissinger to serve as the State Department Legal Advisor. Occupying this position form 1975 - 1977, Leigh was involved in many foreign diplomatic issues. He returned to the law firm of Steptoe & Johnson upon completion of his appointment. Leigh utilized his expertise on international law after the 1979 Iranian Hostage Incident by heading up a team to represent the interests of businesses seeking claims against the Iranian Government in front of a tribunal in The Hague.
Of the many professional organizations Leigh belonged to, he was tapped by the American Society of International Law to be their president from 1981 - 1982. He also served as editor for their law journal and other publications on international law. Serving as a U. S. Member of the Permanent Court of Arbitration in the Hague from 1975 - 1980, Leigh helped to select U. S. nominees to the International Court of Justice. Remaining throughout the 1990s, Leigh became involved in the war crimes trials of Augusto Pinochet, eventually heading up the American Bar Association's (ABA) Task Force on war crimes in the former Yugoslavia. These previous experiences all provided motivation for Leigh to actively support international entities that could sufficiently and effectively arbitrate international disputes and crimes. Leigh eventually served on the ABA Working Group on the International Criminal Court; an entity that was highly influential on the eventual formation of the permanent International Criminal Court that now sits in the Hague under the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court. When the United States ultimately decided not to ratify the treaty and become a member of the International Criminal Court, Leigh took his pen to the page to express his criticism of this decision. Monroe Leigh passed away in 2001 at the age 82.
A more in-depth biography may be found in the Virginia Journal of International Law, Volume 43, Number 1, Fall 2002, page 589: "In Memoriam: Monroe Leigh (1919 - 2001)" by L. Benjamin Ederington.
Scope and Content Information
This collection was donated by the Leigh family in 2003. It is comprised of three major series with numerous subseries, including:
International Criminal Court
Legal Papers
Personal Papers
A primary focus of this collection is Monroe Leigh's work on international disputes and legal issues. Of note are his papers regarding his heavy involvement with the creation of the International Criminal Court as well as the documents focusing on the ABA Task Force on War Crimes in the Former Yugoslavia. Many of the papers delve into legal issues regarding the constitutionality, sovereignty, and jurisdiction of international organizations to arbitrate disputes between multiple foreign entities.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in the following Series and Subseries:
Series 1: International Criminal Court (ICC)
Subseries A: American Bar Association (ABA)
Subseries B: United Nations
Subseries C: ABA War Crimes Task Force - Yugoslavia
Subseries D: Sovereign Immunity
Subseries E: International Law Association Committee on State Immunity
Subseries F: Siracusa Conference - 17 to 21 September 1997
Subseries G: Geneva Conventions
Subseries H: Mixed Articles, Statements, Symposia
Series 2: Legal Papers
Subseries A: State Deparment Advisor
Subseries B: State Department - Permanent Court of Arbitration
Subseries C: Red Cross
Subseries D: International Water Rights
Subseries E: Case Files
Series 3: Personal Papers
Subseries A: Correspondence
Subseries B: University of Virginia Law School Seminar
Subseries C: University of Virginia Student Materials
Contents List
- International Criminal Court (ICC)
  - American Bar Association (ABA)
    - Constitutionality: Memorandum from David Stoelting to General Distribution re: ABA House of Delegates Vote on ICC Recommendation (16 sections of material tabbed and attached), 9 February 2001 (Box-folder 1 - 1)
      Materials supporting Report and Recommendation on ICC to ABA House of Delegates -- ABA Recommendations &, Reports from 1998 and 2001, Letters to President Clinton from U.S. Senators, Members of Congress, retired miltary officers, Jerry Shestack, and WICC, Other statements and supporting articles
    - Constitutionality: Draft Memorandum from Monroe Leigh, Maury Shenk, and Galina Smith re: Constitutionality of Proposed International Criminal Court, 15 February 2000 (Box-folder 1 - 2)
    - Constitutionality: Draft by Monroe Leigh and Maury Shenk, The Constituionality of the International Criminal Court: A Response to Casey and Rivkin, 1 August 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 3)
      Marked draft of response to Senate testimony of Lee A. Casey and David B. Rivkin on constitutional objections to the ICC
    - Constitutionality: Nashville, Draft ABA Recommendation 118B by Section of International Law and Practice, Association of the Bar of the City of New York, Section of Criminal Justice, Section Individual Rights and Responsiblities, and Standing Committee on World Order Under Law, 2 February 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 4)
    - Constitutionality: Email from AdvocacyNet Distribution subject: "On the Record" Vol. 1, Issue 22, 18 July 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 5)
      Summary article on adoption of ICC Statute by Committee of the Whole of the Rome Conference
    - Constitutionality: Fax copy of July 23, 1998 Written Statement of Lee A. Casey & David B. Rivkin, Jr. Before the Subcommittee of International Operations of The Committee on Foreign Relations, U.S. Senate, 29 July 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 6)
    - Constitutionality: Handwritten Draft by Monroe Leigh re: ICC and adoption of the Rome treaty, n.d. (Box-folder 1 - 7)
    - Constitutionality: Draft ABA Section of International Law and Practice Recommendation re: ICC, [1998?] (Box-folder 1 - 8)
      With handwritten edits, report and ICC statute summary attached
    - Constitutionality: Copy of In re Yamashita, [1945] (Box-folder 1 - 9)
      Contains notes, highlights, limited markup
    - Constitutionality: Statement of David L. Scheffer, Ambassador at Large for War Crimes Issues and Head of U.S. Delegation to U.N. Diplomatic Conference on Establishment of ICC, 23 July 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 10)
      Forwarded to Paul R Williams, Executive Director of Public International Law and Policy Group for Carnegie Endowment for International Peace
    - Constitutionality: Miscellaneous Articles and Commentary on issues surrounding adoption of ICC, 1998 -1999 (Box-folder 1 - 11)
      July 20, 1998 ABA article, July 16, 1998 Cato Institute article by Gary Dempsey, August 24, 1998 Forbes magazine commentary, May 1999 American Society of International Law "In Brief"
    - Constitutionality: Miscellaneous photocopies, Scholarly Materials on International Courts, [1943] 1996 [1943] 1996 (Box-folder 1 - 12)
      1943 Cornell L.R. article by Robert E. Cushman - "Ex Parte Quirin et Al - the Nazi Saboteur Case", Except on international courts from Louis Henkin, Foreign Affairs and the United States Constitution (1996)
    - Constitutionality: Fax copy of Draft by David Stoelting Op-Ed re: Rome Conference on the ICC, 1 July 1998 1 July 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 13)
      Handwritten notes and edits included
    - Constitutionality: "Against an International Criminal Court" by Lee A. Casey & David B. Rivkin, Jr., Commentary, May 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 14)
      Note attached, Forwarded via fax to Henry Marshall at U.S. DOJ
    - Constitutionality: "Law Without Borders: The Constitutionality of an International Criminal Court" by Paul D. Marquardt, Columbia Journal of Transnatianal Law, 33:73, 1995 (Box-folder 1 -)
      No markings so removed from collection. Other copy may be found in Box 1 folder 18, in the library or through online academic journal databases such as WestLaw and LexisNexus.
    - Constitutionality: ABA Recommendation 118B by Section of International Law and Practice, [1998?] (Box-folder 1 - 15)
      Association of the Bar of the City of New York, Section of Criminal Justice, Section Individual Rights and Responsiblities, and Standing Committee on World Order Under Law
    - Constitutionality: Emails between Monroe Leigh and Kristen Boon re: memo on constitutionality of U.S. membership in ICC, 13 November 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 16)
    - Constitutionality: Memorandum on Constitutionality of Proposed International Criminal Court, 19 June 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 17)
      Sent from Maury Shenk to Monroe Leigh and including contact information for U.S. delegation in Rome,
    - Constitutionality: Memorandum from Galina Smith to Monroe Leigh re: Territorial courts, 25 June 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 18)
      Includes "Law Without Borders: The Constitutionality of an International Criminal Court" by Paul D. Marquardt, Columbia Journal of Transnatianal Law, 33:73, 1995, Handwritten notes and copies of relevant cases attached
    - Constitutionality: Scholarly articles regarding developments of international criminal court, n.d. (Box-folder 1 - 19)
      Report on the Proposed ICC by The Committee on International Law and the Committee on International Human Rights, "Current Developments" by James C. O'Brien, separate summary by Peter Bekker, and "Proposal for an International Criminal Court" by Quincy Wright from American Journal of Int'l Law.
    - Constitutionality: Report of the Judicial Conference of the United States on the Feasibility and the Relationship to the Federal Judiciary of an International Criminal Court, September 1991 (Box-folder 1 - 20)
      Forwarded to law firm librarian for distribution by Marion A Ott, Administrative Office of the U.S. Courts
    - Constitutionality: Draft memoranda between Monroe Leigh and Maury Shenk re: constitutionality and jurisdiction for international criminal court, 4 April 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 21)
      April 4, 1998 draft by Maury Shenk re: Jurisdiction of International Criminal Court Over U.S. Persons, February 11,1998 draft re: Constitutional objection to International Criminal Court
    - Constitutionality: Draft Memorandum from Galina Smith to Monroe Leigh and Maury Shenk re: Constitutionality of the ICC exercise of judicial power over a defendant who committed a crime in the U.S., 9 June 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 22)
      With handwritten edits and comments
    - Constitutionality: Draft Memorandum from Galina Smith to Monroe Leigh and Maury Shenk re: Constitutionality of the ICC exercise of judicial power over a defendant who committed a crime in the U.S., 1 June 1998 (Box-folder 1 - 23)
      Contains checkmarks
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Fax letter from Mark Jennings to Monroe Leigh, 20 May 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 24)
      Response to questions on collaboration for ICC Rules of Procedure and Evidence
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Fax from David Stoelting to Monroe Leigh forwarding Australian proposal for ICC Rules of Procedure and Evidence, 4 August 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 25)
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Letter from Monroe Leigh to Theodor Meron (enclosures), 5 November 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 26)
      Enclosures: Paper Presented by Michael P. Scharf ("The ICC's Jurisdiction Over the Nationals of Non-Party States: A Reply to Ambassador Scheffer" at August 1999 ABA Section of International Law and Practice, Letter from Monroe Leigh to Samuel Burger regarding acceptance of Rome treaty establishing ICC (with attachments)
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Email from Ambassador Marc Ginsberg to Monroe Leigh re: Gore &,amp, the ICC, 7 October 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 27)
    - Letters to Executive Branch: letter from Monroe Leigh to Lloyd Cutler (enclosures), 30 September 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 28)
      Enclosures: ABA Resolution as approved February 1998, August 1998 Report to ABA Section of International Law and Practice
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Letter from Monroe Leigh to Lisa Brown, Counsel to the Vice President, 27 September 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 29)
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Letter from Monroe Leigh to Greg Stanton of World Federalist Association, 1 November 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 30)
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Letter from Monroe Leigh to Samuel Burger, National Security Advisor, 13 October 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 31)
      Attachments: ABA House of Delegates, Nashville Resolution of Februrary 1998, ABA Section of International Law, Toronto Resolution of August 1998
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Letter from Monroe Leigh to Samuel Burger, National Security Advisor, 12 October 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 32)
      With handwritten notes and edits from Maury D. Shenk
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Letter from David Stoelting to Samuel Burger, Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs, 5 October 1999 (Box-folder 1 - 33)
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Fax from Rona R. Mears to Monroe Leigh forwarding email from David Stoelting on ICC, 13 October 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 1)
    - Letters to Ecexutive Branch: Fax to Mark Ginsberg from Monroe Leigh re: ICC, 29 October 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 2)
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Fax cover and confirmation to John Washburn, 29 October 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 3)
      No indication of what document was forwarded
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Fax from David Stoelting to Monroe Leigh forwarding letter from Michael A. Cooper to Samuel Burger, 29 October 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 4)
    - Letters to Executive Branch: Letter from Mara E. Rudman, Deputy Assistant to the Preseident for National Security Affairs to Monroe Leigh, 8 November 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 5)
      Noting that U.S. would not sign the ICC Treaty and attaching October 20, 1999 Statement Before U.N. General Assembly Sixth Committee re: The Rome Treaty on the International Criminal Court
    - Legal Articles: "The Rocky Shoals of International Law" article by David B. Rivkin, Jr. and Lee A. Casey, The National Interest, Winter 2000/01 (Box-folder 2 - 6)
      With some handwritten notes/markings
    - Legal Articles: "The United States and the International Criminal Court: The Choices Ahead" aritcle by Sarah Sewall and Carl Kaysen, American Academy of Arts and Sciences Committee on International Security Studies (Box-folder -)
    - Legal Articles: Panel Discussion by Association of American Law Schools Panel on the International Criminal Court, 9 January 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 7)
      Post-it attached indicating forwarded from David Aaronson to Monroe Leigh on July 14, 1999
    - Legal Articles: "Symposium: The United States and the International Criminal Court: Achieving a Wider Consensus Through the 'Ithaca Package' " by Ruth Wedgwood, 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 8)
      Page flagged
    - Legal Articles: "The New International Criminal Court: An Uneasy Revolution" by Leila Sadat Wexler and S. Richard Carden, Working Paper No. 99-6-2, Washington University School of Law (Box-folder 2 - 9)
      Handwritten notes and highlighting and page flagged
    - Legal Articles: "The Rome Treaty on the International Criminal Court" ABA Section of International Law and Practice, 10 August 1999 (Box-folder 2 -)
    - Legal Articles: "The International Criminal Court: An American View" article by Ruth Wedgwood, European Journal of International Law 1999 (Box-folder 2 -)
    - Legal Articles: "The ICC's Jurisdiction over the Nationals of Non-Party States: A Reply to Ambassador Scheffer" by Michael P. Scharf, presented at ABA Section of International Law and Practice Annual Meeting, 10 August 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 10)
      Handwritten notes and markings, Extensive notes on back
    - Legal Articles: Selected Articles on the International Criminal Court by Ruth Wedgwood, 1995 - 2000 (Box-folder 2 - 11)
      1) "The Case for a Permanent War Crimes Court", 2) "Fiddling in Rome: America and the International Criminal Court", 3) "The International Criminal Court: An American View", 4) "Achieving a Wider Consensus Through the 'Ithaca Package,", 5) "Courting Disaster: The U.S. Takes a Stand"
    - Legal Articles: Email from Bruce Broomhall to Monroe Leigh re: Diane's memo, 25 August 2000 (Box-folder 2 - 12)
      Attaching "International Criminal Tribunals: An Institution the United States Can Support" by Diane F. Orentlicher
    - Legal Articles: "The ICC's Jurisdiction over the Nationals of Non-Party States: A Reply to Ambassador Scheffer" by Michael P. Scharf, as presented October 28, 1999 at National Security Law in a Changing World: The Ninth Annual Review of the Field 28 October 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 13)
      Handwritten notes and markings
    - Legal Articles: Draft of "High Crimes and Misconceptions: The ICC and Non-Party States" by Madeline Morris, n.d. (Box-folder 2 - 14)
    - Legal Articles: "U.S. Objections to the Statute of the International Criminal Court: A Brief Response" by Bartram S. Brown, NYU Journal of International Law and Politics, Summer 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 15)
      Signature: Monroe Leigh
    - Legal Articles: Letter from Monroe Leigh to Lea D. Browning with enclosures, 24 November 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 16)
      Enclosures, both with markings as photocopied: "The ICC's Jurisdiction over the Nationals of Non-Party States: A Reply to Ambassador Scheffer" by Michael P. Scharf, as presented October 28, 1999 at Natioanl Security Law in a Changing World: The Ninth Annual Review of the Field, and DRAFT of "High Crimes and Misconceptions: The ICC and Non-Party States" by Madeline Morris
    - Legal Articles: "The United States and the International Criminal Court: Achieving a Wider Consent through the Ithaca Package" article by Ruth Wedgwood, forthcoming in Cornell International Law Journal (Box-folder 2 -)
      Duplicate of article in Series I: ICC, Subseries A: ABA, Box 2 Folder 8
    - Legal Articles: Draft "The ICC's New Legal Landscape: The Need to Expand the United States Domestic Jurisdiction to Prosecute Genocide, War Crimes, and Crimes Against Humanity" by Douglass Cassel for Fordham International Law Journal, November 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 17)
    - Legal Articles: "The International Criminal Court: An American View" article by Ruth Wedgwood, European Journal of International Law (1999) AND "A Response to the American View as Presented by Ruth Wedgwood" 1999 (Box-folder 2 - 18)
    - Press Clippings: Photocopy, "Rome Treaty Marks Historic Moment in International Criminal Law" by David Stoelting in the New York Law Journal, 28 August 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 19)
      With note from David
    - Press Clippings: 10 articles from October/November 2001 printed via LexisNexis search 28 November 2001 (Box-folder 2 - 20)
      With handwritten markings, flagged and note attached - "The Institute for Global Legal Studies Inaugural Colloqium: The UN and the Protection of Human Rights: Introduction" by Stephen H. Legomsky for the Washington University Journal of Law &,amp, Policy, "International Court Should Try Defendants" by Leila Sadat, St. Louis-Post Dispatch, "ICC Establishment Pushed by Experts" for BusinessWorld, "International Court is Not 'War Menace' " by Stephen Rickard as letter to the editor, Washington Times, "The Need for Global Justice" by Rob Gaudet, The Stanford Daily, "Fate of bin Laden Strengthens Case for Permanet UN Court" for Agence France Presse, "Our Opinion: Even Superpowers Still Need Friends" editorial for The Atlanta Journal and Constitution, "A New International Spirit, If the U.S. Can Combat Terrorism, It Can Cooperate to Pursue Justice" by Diane Marie Amann, The San Francisco Chronicle, "Court Order" by David J. Scheffer, letter to the editor, Foreign Affairs, "Time to Recognise Courts Not Bombs" by Rob Bennett, Morning Star
    - Press Clippings: Photocopy, "The Pitfalls of Global Justice" by Ruth Wedgwood, New York Times Op-Ed, 10 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 21)
    - Press Clippings: Photocopy, "A Worldwide Criminal Court", the Washington Post, 12 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 22)
      With highlighting
    - Clipping, "U.N. Conference to Draft War Crimes Treaty" by Charles Trueheart, Washington Post, 14 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 23)
    - Press Clippings: Photocopy, "Arrest Refines Task of U.N. Conference" by Charles Trueheart, Washington Post, 16 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 24)
    - Press Clippings: Photocopy, "China: War Crimes Court Should Be Limited", brief, Washington Post, 17 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 25)
    - Press Clippings: Email from Lea Browning to Monroe Leigh and others re: ICC Opposistion [sic]: Ashcroft, 15 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 26)
      Forwarding information from the World Federalist on Washington Post announcement
    - Press Clippings: Email from Lea Browning to Monroe Leigh and others re: ICC -- Rape as war crime, 15 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 27)
      Forwarding June 14, 1998 article from the New York Times, "An Old Scourage fo War Becomes Its Latest Crime" by Barbara Crossette
    - Press Clippings: Email from Lea Browning blind-copied to Monroe Leigh re: ICC -- The Economist, 12 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 28)
      Forwarding information on 2 articles in The Economist, June 13, 1998 on ICC
    - Press Clippings: Photocopies, "Drive Opens for International Criminal Court" by James Blitz and "Beyond Nuremberg" by Kofi Annan for Financial Times Mandate, 16 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 29)
    - Press Clippings: Press Briefing by USG for Legal Affairs and UN Legal Counsel, 18 May 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 30)
    - Press Clippings: Photocopies of New York Times articles from 18 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 31)
      Photocopy, "U.S. Argues Against Strongly Independent War Crimes Prosecutor" by Alessandra Stanley, "A Strong International Court" editorial
    - Press Clippings: Photocopies of Washington Post articles from 18 June 1998 (Box-folder 2 - 32)
      Photocopy, "Clout Without a Country: The Power of International Lobbies" by Charles Trueheart, brief, "U.S. at Odds with Allies Over Court"